Display a chat input widget.

Parameters
----------
placeholder : str
    A placeholder text shown when the chat input is empty. This
    defaults to ``"Your message"``. For accessibility reasons, you
    should not use an empty string.

key : str or int
    An optional string or integer to use as the unique key for the widget.
    If this is omitted, a key will be generated for the widget based on
    its content. No two widgets may have the same key.

max_chars : int or None
    The maximum number of characters that can be entered. If this is
    ``None`` (default), there will be no maximum.

accept_file : bool or str
    Whether the chat input should accept files. This can be one of the
    following values:

    - ``False`` (default): No files are accepted and the user can only
      submit a message.
    - ``True``: The user can add a single file to their submission.
    - ``"multiple"``: The user can add multiple files to their
      submission.

    When the widget is configured to accept files, the accepted file
    types can be configured with the ``file_type`` parameter.

    By default, uploaded files are limited to 200 MB each. You can
    configure this using the ``server.maxUploadSize`` config option.
    For more information on how to set config options, see
    |config.toml|_.

    .. |config.toml| replace:: ``config.toml``
    .. _config.toml: https://docs.streamlit.io/develop/api-reference/configuration/config.toml

file_type : str, Sequence[str], or None
    The allowed file extension(s) for uploaded files. This can be one
    of the following types:

    - ``None`` (default): All file extensions are allowed.
    - A string: A single file extension is allowed. For example, to
      only accept CSV files, use ``"csv"``.
    - A sequence of strings: Multiple file extensions are allowed. For
      example, to only accept JPG/JPEG and PNG files, use
      ``["jpg", "jpeg", "png"]``.

disabled : bool
    Whether the chat input should be disabled. This defaults to
    ``False``.

on_submit : callable
    An optional callback invoked when the chat input's value is submitted.

args : tuple
    An optional tuple of args to pass to the callback.

kwargs : dict
    An optional dict of kwargs to pass to the callback.

Returns
-------
None, str, or dict-like
    The user's submission. This is one of the following types:

    - ``None``: If the user didn't submit a message or file in the last
      rerun, the widget returns ``None``.
    - A string: When the widget is not configured to accept files and
      the user submitted a message in the last rerun, the widget
      returns the user's message as a string.
    - A dict-like object: When the widget is configured to accept files
      and the user submitted a message and/or file(s) in the last
      rerun, the widget returns a dict-like object with two attributes,
      ``text`` and ``files``.

    When the widget is configured to accept files and the user submits
    something in the last rerun, you can access the user's submission
    with key or attribute notation from the dict-like object. This is
    shown in Example 3 below.

    The ``text`` attribute holds a string, which is the user's message.
    This is an empty string if the user only submitted one or more
    files.

    The ``files`` attribute holds a list of UploadedFile objects.
    The list is empty if the user only submitted a message. Unlike
    ``st.file_uploader``, this attribute always returns a list, even
    when the widget is configured to accept only one file at a time.

    The UploadedFile class is a subclass of BytesIO, and therefore is
    "file-like". This means you can pass an instance of it anywhere a
    file is expected.

Examples
--------
**Example 1: Pin the chat input widget to the bottom of your app**

When ``st.chat_input`` is used in the main body of an app, it will be
pinned to the bottom of the page.

>>> import streamlit as st
>>>
>>> prompt = st.chat_input("Say something")
>>> if prompt:
...     st.write(f"User has sent the following prompt: {prompt}")

.. output ::
    https://doc-chat-input.streamlit.app/
    height: 350px

**Example 2: Use the chat input widget inline**

The chat input can also be used inline by nesting it inside any layout
container (container, columns, tabs, sidebar, etc) or fragment. Create
chat interfaces embedded next to other content, or have multiple
chatbots!

>>> import streamlit as st
>>>
>>> with st.sidebar:
>>>     messages = st.container(height=300)
>>>     if prompt := st.chat_input("Say something"):
>>>         messages.chat_message("user").write(prompt)
>>>         messages.chat_message("assistant").write(f"Echo: {prompt}")

.. output ::
    https://doc-chat-input-inline.streamlit.app/
    height: 350px

**Example 3: Let users upload files**

When you configure your chat input widget to allow file attachments, it
will return a dict-like object when the user sends a submission. You
can access the user's message through the ``text`` attribute of this
dictionary. You can access a list of the user's submitted file(s)
through the ``files`` attribute. Similar to ``st.session_state``, you
can use key or attribute notation.

>>> import streamlit as st
>>>
>>> prompt = st.chat_input(
>>>     "Say something and/or attach an image",
>>>     accept_file=True,
>>>     file_type=["jpg", "jpeg", "png"],
>>> )
>>> if prompt and prompt.text:
>>>     st.markdown(prompt.text)
>>> if prompt and prompt["files"]:
>>>     st.image(prompt["files"][0])

.. output ::
    https://doc-chat-input-file-uploader.streamlit.app/
    height: 350px


